"Yerba Mate and Cancer:
Do Its Benefits Outweigh Its Risks?"
Yerba mate teas have been
consumed for centuries
by the South American
indigenous peoples,
and today, certain regions
of Latin America
have a quart (950 ml) a day.
So, understanding
what's in mate is important,
particularly if there are
"High levels of carcinogenic
polycyclic aromatic
hydrocarbons,"
including one of the most
potent, benzopyrene,
which is known to be
cancer-causing in humans
and is found concentrated
in cigarette smoke,
grilled and barbequed meat,
and mate.
These carcinogenic compounds
are fat soluble, though,
and may not readily transfer
from the mate leaves
into the water.
It turns out transfer rates
can be anywhere
between 1 percent
to 50 percent,
depending on
the brewing method.
But levels in mate leaves
are so high
that even if about five percent
transfers into the tea,
heavy mate consumption could be
the benzopyrene equivalent
to smoking
about four cigarettes.
Each cigarette has
around 10 nanograms,
so that would be,
like, 40 nanograms,
or the amount
of carcinogenic benzopyrene
found in about one-tenth
of a serving
of grilled chicken.
Okay, but a direct comparison
between breathing in
the chemical
versus eating or drinking it
may be inaccurate
because we absorb it
differently.
Maybe, but when the levels
of a breakdown product
of these kinds of chemicals
was measured in the urine
of smokers
versus mate drinkers,
those who drank more than two
or four cups (480 or 960 ml)
of mate a day
appeared to have
as much of these carcinogens
flowing through their systems
as smokers.
Okay, but does this
actually translate out
into higher cancer rates?
I mean, mate has
more antioxidant power
than green tea,
significantly increasing
the antioxidant capacity
of the bloodstreams
of those randomized
to drink it.
So, might the good
outweigh the bad?
Apparently not.
Mate drinkers have
about double the odds of cancers
of the mouth, throat,
esophagus, and voicebox.